Capital Region Transgender Community Archive; Collection apap185
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
The Capital District Transgender Community Archive Collection1969-2006
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Capital District Transgender Community Archive
apap185
3.37 cubic ft.
The Capital District Transgender Community Archive Collection contains material pertaining to local trangender history. This collections contains a large variety of publications about transgenderism.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted with the exception of several marked folders. These folders are restricted due to the graphic nature of some and others are restricted upon request of the donor.
Acquisition Information
Susan Poe donated these papers to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections in a series of donations in 2004-2006.
Organizational Sketch
This collection is a gathering of material that reflects the history of the local transgender community. A majority of the material belonged to Winnie Brandt, the former President of the Transgender Independence Club, also known as TGIC. Brandt, along with other transgender community members, produced as well as collected a large number of local, regional, and national publications. The TGIC and TVIC were two local transgender groups based in Albany New York. TGIC was founded in 1971, and at the time was the only membership organization in the Albany area for transgender people where enrollment stayed confidential. TGIC held weekly social gatherings for transgender people to socialize with other transgender people or partake in discussion about issues affecting the transgender community. Unfortunately the club was disbanded in the early 2000s due to much conflict within the group. A group similar to TGIC was the Albany Gender Project, founded in 2001 by Susan Poe and Helen Farrell. The project worked to improve the conditions for transgender people in the Capital Region as well as promote and advocate educational services for them. The Albany Gender Project also hosted bimonthly meetings where members held forums, listened to guest speakers, and were connected to the social services they needed.
For the transgender community, this collection shows "how we've been a real community with a collective life and traditions and continuity. It shows what our issues have been, what we keep rehashing, what works, what doesn't, and who the personalities have been and how they've helped the community." (Taken from the final issue of Trannies in Love).
Scope and Contents
The Capital Region Transgender Community Archive is a unique collection of local and regional newsletters and documents from the 1970s to the present. The collection includes the TVIC newsletter (1972-1984), TGIC newsletter (1987-2001), and issues of other local, regional, and national publications. National titles include TV-TS Tapestry, Transgender Tapestry, Femme Mirror, and Cross-Talk. The researcher should note that TV-TS Tapestry, TV/TS Tapestry, TV-TS Tapestry Journal, and Transgender Tapestry are the same publication, the title just changed throughout the years. Regional titles include Our Sorority, The Journal of Gender Studies, Outreach Beacon, and Rosebuds. In addition to the TVIC and TGIC newsletters local pulications in this collection include all issues of Trannies in Love, an issue of TV Entertainers and an issue of Metroland. Also available in the collection are posters, fliers, some organizational records, videos, electronic records, and material from the Albany Gender Project.
Researchers interested in using this collection will be required to sign a document agreeing to not disclose personally identifiable information from this collection.
Separated Materials
The archivist transferred three monographs: A Quiet Song, A Little Storm written by Mary Ellen Reinhard, Dressing Up written by Peter Ackroyd, and Transformations written by Mariette Pathy Allen to the book division of Special Collections. These will be catalogued and included at a later date in the University Library Catalog.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized chronologically. There are no series.
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Human Sexuality and Gender Identity; Albany, New York; Community organization--New York (State)--Albany; Transgender people--New York (State); Transgenderism--New York (State); Magazines (periodicals); Newspapers; Newsletters; Correspondence; Electronic documents; Albany Gender Project
- Albany Gender Project, Attorney D. Broda and B.J. Hahn Gravesite Memorial Day, 2002 (Video-tape 1)
- Albany Gender Project Brochures, Newsletters, Constitution, and Papers, [RESTRICTED], 2002-2003; Undated (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Must consult archivist before viewing this material.
- Albany Gender Project, D. Broda talking about Name Changing and Inheritance, B.J. Hahn Gravesite Memorial Day, and Poe and LaVedure on Homo Radio, 2002-2003 (Video-tape 2)
- Albany Gender Project, Gallery, 2002 (Video-tape 3)
- Albany Gender Project, W. Lemily and W. Callan Williams, 2002 (Video-tape 4)
- Albany Transgender Social Center, [RESTRICTED], 2005-2006 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 2)
- Albany Transgender Social Center, Civil Rights Series, 2005 (Dvd 1)
- Albany Transgender Social Center Flyer, 2005 (Oversized 1)
- Albany TV Entertainers, 1987-1990; Undated (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 3)
- The American Crossdresser, Undated (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 4)
- Background on TGIC demise and other conflicts, [RESTRICTED], 2002-2003 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 5)
- Bobbi Jo Hahn, [RESTRICTED], 2000-2001; Undated (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 6)
- Book of Program Transcripts from "Coming Together" Convention, 1987 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 7)
- Building a Dynamic Transgender Community, Undated (Video-tape 5)
- Capital District Transgender Alliance (CDTGA ) E-Group Messages, [RESTRICTED], 2005 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 8)
- Cross-Talk, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 9)
- Cross-Talk, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 10)
- Cross-Talk, 1995 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 11)
- Cross-Talk, 1995-1996 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 12)
- Cross-Talk, 1996 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 13-14)
- "A Crash Course for Confused Cross-Dressers" and "Success Insurance," Souvenir from 1986 Fantasia Fair, 1969 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 15-16)
- "The Dance of Samantha McGee", ca. 1984 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 17)
- Fantasia Fair, An Experience to Remember, 1993 (Video-tape 6)
- Fantasia Fair Photographs, 1988 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 18)
- Femme Mirror, 1986-1988 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 19)
- Femme Mirror, 1989-1990 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 20)
- Femme Mirror, 1991 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 21)
- Femme Mirror, 1992 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 22)
- Femme Mirror, 1993 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 23)
- Femme Mirror, 1994 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 24)
- Femme Mirror, 1995 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 25)
- Femme Mirror, 1996 (Box 1 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 26)
- Femme Mirror, 1996-1997 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 1)
- Femme Mirror, 1997 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 2)
- Femme Mirror, 1998 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 3)
- Femme Mirror, 1998-1999 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 4)
- Flyer for Susan Poe's Fulton Street Gallery Summer Residency, Undated (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 5)
- GENDA, Undated (Video-tape 7)
- Hartford TVIC and Sugar and Spice Sorority Newsletters, 1973; 1974; Undated (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 6)
- Helen Boyd, "Building Alliances and Community", Undated (Dvd 2)
- Journal of Gender Studies, 1992-1995 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 8)
- Loving My Poops, Fulton Street Gallery, 2002 (Video-tape 8)
- Metroland, 2002 (Oversized 1)
- My Treasured Friends Books, [RESTRICTED], Undated (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 8)
- Our Sorority, 1981-1989 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 9)
- Our Sorority, 1990-1991 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 10)
- Outreach Beacon, 1987-1989 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 11)
- Provincetown Advocate, 1975 (Oversized 1)
- Rosebuds, 1987-1989 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 12)
- Rosebuds, 1990-1991 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 13)
- Rosebuds, 1991-1992 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 14)
- Rosebuds, 1992-1993 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 15)
- Rosebuds, 1993-1994 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 16)
- Trannies in Love Fundraising Flyers and Event Flyers [RESTRICTED], 2003; Undated (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 17)
- Trannies in Love, Issues 1-8, ca. 2004 (Oversized 1)
- Trannies in Love Posters and Others, 2003; Undated (Dvd 3)
- Trans E-Lists, TCDO and TGIC, 2000-2004 (Dvd 4)
- Trans Gender Forum, Vols. 1 & 2, 1995-1996 (Dvd 5)
- Transgender Tapestry, 1995-1996 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 18)
- Transgender Tapestry, 1996 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 19)
- Transgender Tapestry, 1997-1998 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 20)
- Transgender Tapestry, 1998 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 21)
- Transgender Tapestry, 1999 (Box 2 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 22)
- Transgender Tapestry, 2000 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 1)
- Transgender Tapestry, 2001 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 2)
- Transgender Tapestry, 2002 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 3)
- Transgender Tapestry, 2004-2005 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 4)
- Transgenderist, [RESTRICTED], 1992; 1994 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 5)
- Transgenderist, [RESTRICTED], 1995-1996 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 6)
- Transgenderist, [RESTRICTED], 1997-1998 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 7)
- Transgenderist, [RESTRICTED], 1999-2000 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 8)
- Transgenderist, [RESTRICTED], 2001 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 9)
- Transvestia, 1986 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 10)
- Transvestite Sex Review, [RESTRICTED], Undated (Oversized 1)
- TGIC, Butterfly, EON Joint Newsletter, [RESTRICTED], 1987-1989 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 11)
- TGIC E-List Archive, [RESTRICTED], 2000-2003 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 12-18)
- TGIC News, [RESTRICTED], 1990-1993 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 19)
- TGIC Pamphlets and Price Schedule, 1987; Undated (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 20)
- TVIC Journal, [RESTRICTED], 1974-1976 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 21)
- TVIC Journal, [RESTRICTED], 1977-1978 (Box 3 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 22)
- TVIC Journal, [RESTRICTED], 1979-1980 (Box 4 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 1)
- TVIC Journal, [RESTRICTED], 1981-1984 (Box 4 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 2)
- TVIC Membership List, [RESTRICTED], 1967 (Box 4 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 3)
- TVIC Newsletter, [RESTRICTED], 1973-1974 (Box 4 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 4)
- TV Times, Article talking about first Fantasia Fair, [RESTRICTED], ca. 1975 (Box 4 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 5)
- TV-TS Tapestry, 1988-1989 (Box 4 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 6)
- TV-TS Tapestry, 1989-1990 (Box 4 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 7)
- TV-TS Tapestry, 1991 (Box 4 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 8)
- TV-TS Tapestry, 1991-1992 (Box 5 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 1)
- TV/TS Tapestry, 1992-1993 (Box 5 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 2)
- TV/TS Tapestry Journal, 1993-1994 (Box 5 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 3)
- TV/TS Tapestry Journal, 1994-1995 (Box 5 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 4)
- TV/TS Tapestry Journal, 1995 (Box 5 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 5)
- Who's Who in the Transgendered Community, 1993 (Box 5 (The Capital District Transgender Community Archive), Folder 6)